in this video we're going to finally
start talking about how Spinners are
used in particle physics the area of
physics that helps us understand
fundamental particles is called Quantum
field Theory or
qft now qft is an enormous topic and it
normally takes three courses at The
Graduate level to cover the basics of it
there's no way I can cover all of qft in
this series instead I'm going to cover
just a small sliver of qft which which
is the dur equation the dur equation is
the equation that governs the behavior
of free Spin 1 half particles in the
absence of any forces or
interactions this will hopefully give
you a sense of how Spinners are used in
the larger topic of quantum field
Theory however before I get to the
direct equation I'm going to use this
video to give you an overview of quantum
field Theory as a whole I'm not going to
go into a lot of detail but I'm going to
try laying out a general map of qft and
show you how the direct equation and
Spinners fit into
it so frequently I see Quantum field
Theory as being composed of two main sub
areas particle physics and condensed
matter physics I'm not sure if
everything in qft belongs to one of
these two categories but these are
definitely the two main sub
areas particle physics involves the
collisions and interactions of
particles this this involves the study
of things like a photon scattering off
an electron an electron and its
antimatter counterpart the positron
annihilating into two photons a neutron
undergoing radioactive decay into a
proton electron and anti neutrino or
quarks being bounced together into
protons and neutrons through gluon
exchange
particles particle physics typically
involves a relatively small number of
particles so that you can keep track of
all the particles individually
on the other hand condensed matter
physics involves the collective behavior
of a huge number of particles the number
of particles is so huge that we don't
normally keep track of individual
particles and instead we look at the
statistical behavior of particles
together as a huge
group the collective behavior of a huge
number of particles is what lets us
understand the states of matter like
solids liquids and
gases these states of matter are not
programmed into the fundamental laws of
physics instead states of matter arise
out of the collective behavior of
particles together condensed matter
physics also allows us to study more
exotic states of matter that we don't
normally see in everyday life such as
Bose Einstein condensates and super
fluids and it also lets us study super
conductivity so Quantum field Theory
lets us understand a lot of things but
what exactly is it
you'll often hear people say that qft
treats particles as excitations in
various fields for example electrons are
viewed as excitations in the electron
field and photons are viewed as
excitations in the photon field but what
exactly does this mean to understand
this I'm going to draw a bunch of areas
of physics in a cube shape in the
starting corner of the cube we have
Newtonian physics from here we can
expand out in three different directions
using special relativity quantum
mechanics and classical field
theory if we try to combine quantum
mechanics and special relativity we get
relativistic quantum mechanics this
Theory can help us predict some things
such as the existence of antimatter but
as a whole the theory is kind of broken
and
inconsistent to save it we need to use
field theory if we combine quantum
mechanics with field Theory we get
non-relativistic Quantum field Theory
this can help us understand some of the
condensed matter systems I mentioned
above however when it comes to particle
physics where particles are usually
traveling at or close to the speed of
light non-relativistic qft fails because
it doesn't incorporate special
relativity if we combine field Theory
with special relativity we get
relativistic field Theory which lets us
model fields where waves can travel at
or close to the speed of light but this
does not obey the rules of quantum
mechanics finally if we combine quantum
mechanics special relativity and field
Theory together we get relativistic
Quantum field Theory this is usually
what people are talking about when they
say
qft so to properly understand Quantum
field Theory we need to understand
special relativity quantum mechanics and
classical field Theory and understand
how they all fit
together so let's start with special
relativity the two postulates of special
relativity are that the laws of physics
are the same in all inertial reference
frames and that the speed of light in a
vacuum is also the same in all inertial
reference frames what this really means
is that we need to change from using the
Galilean Transformations from Newtonian
physics and upgrade to use Lorent
Transformations for Galilean
Transformations time is universal in all
reference frames and position transforms
with basic velocity addition
rules however with Lorent
Transformations the time and space
coordinates mix into each other an
important idea in special relativity is
that time and space should be treated on
the same level unified together into
space
time because of this it's easy to see
that Schrodinger's equation for single
particle position wave functions does
not transform relativistically in space
time because it has a first derivative
in time and a second derivative in space
so space and time are not treated on the
same
level if you like you can try
transforming the T and X variables in
Schrodinger's equation using a Galilean
transformation and you'll find that the
result still looks like Schrodinger's
equation on the other hand the Lorent
Transformations will change the form of
Schrodinger's
equation this contrasts with Maxwell's
equations for electricity and magnetism
where time and space have the same
number of
derivatives Maxwell's equations retain
their form when we transform them with
Lorent Transformations so they are
compatible with special
relativity also just as special
relativity unites time and space into a
single four-dimensional object called
SpaceTime and energy and momentum are
also united into a single
four-dimensional object called four
momentum the lengths of the four
position and four momentum vectors are
normally measured using a distance
function called the minovsky metric
which is given by this Matrix here
denoted by
Ada the menovsky metric is important in
special relativity because it is
unchanged by Lorent
Transformations the menovsky length of
the four position Vector is the
SpaceTime interval s and the minkovsky
length of the for momentum Vector is the
object's rest mass m these quantities
are invariant in all coordinate
systems now let's talk about classical
field theories when you first start
learning Newtonian physics you usually
learn it in the language of forces
acting on
particles for example we can calculate
the gravitational force of a plan
on a small mass or electric forces
between charges or the magnetic force of
a current carrying wire on a Charged
particle however it's common to take
these particle theories and upgrade them
to field theories for example instead of
calculating the forces for a ton of
different objects around a planet we can
associate a gravitational field with the
planet which is defined everywhere in
space and time and use that to calculate
forces
instead we can do something similar with
electric fields and magnetic
fields Fields can be further abstracted
to potentials which are also defined
everywhere in space and time we can
derive the fields related to forces by
taking derivatives of potential
fields we can even find that these
fields have a life of their own for
example the electromagnetic field can
carry energy through space in the
absence of any sources such as electric
charges or current these electromagnetic
waves are what light
is when dealing with Advanced physics
problems it's common to use the lonian
formulation of mechanics where the lran
is equal to a particle's kinetic energy
minus its potential
energy we can plug the lran into the
oiler lrange equations to get the
equation of motion for the particle
Loosely speaking this is a more abstract
version of Newton's fals ma where forces
are replaced with gradients of potential
energies and M * a is replaced with the
time derivative of
momentum a basic example is the simple
harmonic oscillator which is a mass on a
spring the kinetic energy of the mass is
12 * Mass * velocity squared and I'm
using x dot to denote a time derivative
of the position X and the potential
energy is 1 12 * the spring constant K *
x^ s where X is the displacement from
the neutral
position plugging this into the oiler
lrange equation we get that the spring
Force KX equals mass time
acceleration which is Hook's
law this has sinusoidal
Solutions this partial derivative of the
lran with respect to x dot is often
called the canonical or conjugate
momentum P which often gets used in
hamiltonian
mechanics in this case p is just
masstimes
velocity it's possible to combine a
bunch of simple harmonic oscillators
into a continuous scalar
field we can start by taking two
oscillators labeled one and two and
tying them together with a rubber
band each oscillator gets its own
kinetic energy term and its own spring
potential energy term there's also a
coupling potential energy term for the
rubber band that depends on the
difference of the mass positions and an
elastic constant Kappa if the
expositions are the same this term does
nothing but if there's a difference in
the expositions there is a restoring
force that pulls the masses back
together so the lran for this system
looks like
this using the oiler lrange equations
for X1 and X2 we get two coupled
equations of motion for the two masses
which can be written as this Matrix
equation now coupled equations that mix
X1 and X2 are difficult to solve however
something happens if we look for the
igen vectors of this Matrix we get a
solution Vector that is directly
proportional to the
acceleration which has an easy
solution these Solutions are called
normal modes or igen
modes the first igen Vector is 1 one
with an IG value of K and the second IG
Vector is 1 1 with an IG value of k + 2
Kappa the first igen Vector gives a
normal mode solution where the two
masses move together the second IG
Vector gives a normal mode solution
where the two masses move in opposite
ways note how the igen values correspond
to the solution
frequencies since these two solutions
are completely independent we can add
them together in arbitrary linear
combinations to get a general set of
solutions for the
system if we continue to add more and
more oscillators each labeled with a
position X I where I is an integer we
get an infinite field of
oscillators usually we turn this system
on its side so that the oscillators move
in the FI
Direction and X becomes an axis for
identifying the location of a specific
oscillator f of x gives the height of
the oscillator at location
X since X is a continuous variable we
have to imagine these oscillators are
infinitely close to
together it becomes less useful to talk
about the total kinetic energy of an
entire field instead we talk about
kinetic energy density the kinetic
energy density is just the amount of
kinetic energy of masses in one unit of
space we can use the standard kinetic
energy formula 12 mv^ s but here the
velocity is the time derivative of the
field amplitude so this is a function
that measures how fast a mass is shaking
at a given X
location there's also the potential
energy density which is the amount of
potential energy in the masses per one
unit of
space there's the spring potential
energy which is 1 12 K * the squared
amplitude of the field relative to the
neutral
position there's also the potential
energy of the rubber bands joining the
masses together which is now given by a
gradient term which measures the
separation of neighboring masses in the
FI
Direction now many sources do a few
redefinitions of the terms here the
elastic constant Kappa is often set
equal to the mass m and the field fi is
often redefined as fi Tilda using a
scaling factor of the square root of M
this allows the M value to to be
absorbed into the field
amplitude and this K Over M term is
often defined as a new Mass term M Tilda
squared so you'll often see scalar
Fields defined with these formulas for
the kinetic and potential energy
densities although from now on I'm going
to stop writing the tildas in these
formulas so when we move to field Theory
our lonian formula from before
gets replaced with a lran density
formula where all the quantities are
densities per unit of
space we also get a field version of the
oiler lrange
equations looking at the lran density
for our field of masses on Springs
plugging this into the field version of
the oiler lrange equation we get this
equation of motion for the
field just like we saw with the system
of coupled oscillators for this field
equation there are multiple independent
Solutions of multiple different
frequencies the most basic solution
modes are
sinusoidal here Omega is the waves
angular frequency in time and K is the
waves angular frequency in space also
called The Wave
number K and Omega must obey this Mass
relation here
we can take any linear combination of
these Solutions with different wave
numbers to get another
solution although since the wave number
K is a continuous variable the most
General linear combination is done with
an integral over
K it's also common to write these basic
solution modes using complex
exponentials instead of
sinusoids if we extend our lran into a
three-dimensional field with Y and Z
directions we get this equation of
motion which is called the Klein Gordon
[Music]
equation and just as we defined
canonical momentum P for individual
particles using a derivative of the lran
we can also Define the canonical field
momentum density Pi using a derivative
of the lran
density in the case of the Klein field
the momentum density just measures how
fast masses are vibrating at a specific
location in
space so hopefully you now understand
some of the basic ideas in field Theory
a field is described by a lonian density
which keeps track of the kinetic and
potential energy densities at specific
points in the field the lran density can
be used to derive the equations of
motion for the field
and it's often easiest to consider the
most basic solutions to this equation
which are the normal modes and then add
these normal modes together in a linear
combination to get a more complicated
field
solution now one last thing I've talked
about solving problems using the lonian
formulation of mechanics but I should
also mention the alternative hamiltonian
formulation of
mechanics we can use the LR in L to
define a related quantity H called the
hamiltonian like this this formula
converts equations that use position and
velocity into equations that use
position and canonical momentum
P however in simple cases where the
lonian terms obey some specific
properties the hamiltonian is simply
defined as the total energy of the
system which is kinetic plus potential
energy
our coupled oscillator system is an
example of one of these special cases
and we can get its hamiltonian just by
starting with the lran and changing the
signs on the potential energy terms and
also replacing x dot with P in the
kinetic
terms we can also Define the hamiltonian
density in field Theory this converts
equations to use canonical field
momentum pi
again in the simplest cases the
hamiltonian density is just the total
energy density of the
field so for the Klein Gordon field we
can get the hamiltonian density just by
starting with the lonian density and
changing the signs on the potential
energy terms and also replacing fi dot
terms with canonical field momentum
density
Pi we'll see the hamiltonian and
hamiltonian density used later in
quantum
mechanics next let's take a look at
mechanics unfortunately the postulates
of quantum mechanics are not as easy to
State as the postulates of special
relativity the quantum postulates
involve a lot of terminology like
Hilbert spaces her Mission operators and
expected values but I'll try to review
the most important Concepts in quantum
mechanics now many of these key Concepts
will carry over to Quantum field
theory in classical mechanics the state
of a particle is given by its position
and
momentum basically where it is and where
it's going the state of the particle
then evolves in time according to
Newton's Laws Newton's Laws can be
reformulated in many different ways
including Hamilton's equations which use
the hamiltonian age
which is sort of like the total energy
of the system in quantum mechanics the
state of a system is given by an
abstract State Vector s of T the state
evolves in time according to the
schinger equation which contains the
hamiltonian operator H
hat this state Vector Sai lives in a
vector space called a complex Hilbert
space which is denoted with a curly
h a complex Hilbert space has the
following
properties coefficients in linear
combinations are complex
numbers there is also an inner product
or dotproduct between vectors which is
often denoted like this with angle
brackets and Performing this inner
product in the opposite order gives the
complex conjugate of the original
result Hilbert spaces also have a
property called completeness which
basically means we can do calculus and
do derivatives and integrals in the ways
we
expect in quantum mechanics the results
of measurements are always
probabilistic the probability of the
state s collapsing onto some other state
a during a measurement is given by the
squared magnitude of the inner product
of s and a this is called born's
Rule here we call a a bra vector and
call S A KET Vector since their inner
product forms a bra KET a bra Vector is
given by the complex conjugate transpose
of a cat Vector this operation is also
called the Herm Mission conjugate and is
denoted by a
dagger the result of this bracket is
called the probability amplitude for the
state
transition and the actual probability
value is the squared magn itude of this
probability
amplitude in quantum mechanics
observable quantities like position
momentum and energy are each given a
Herm Mission operator with Herm Mission
meaning the operator equals its own Herm
Mission
conjugate we use hats over top of the
variables to indicate that these are
linear operators not just ordinary real
variables if a particle is in a state
with an exactly known position X we
denote this state by the cat Vector X
this is an igen state of the position
operator which produces the exact known
position X as an En
value similarly we can also get exact
momentum IG States for the momentum
operator and exact energy IG States for
the hamiltonian
operator it can be shown that since
these operators are Herm Mission their
igen values for the measurable
quantities are always
real also note that since it's
impossible for one position ion state to
collapse onto a different position IG
State the inner product of two different
position igen states is
zero we can summarize the inner product
of position igen states using the direct
Delta which is zero everywhere except
when the positions are the
same if a general State s of T is not
not an exactly known position igen State
we can still expand the S KET as a
linear combination of position igen
states where the coefficients on all the
Cs are the probability amplitudes for
collapsing onto that specific position
igen State since X is a continuous
variable we should really write this sum
as an integral over all possible
position states where the probability
amplitude for each position is given by
this function s of T in X this is also
called the position wave
function if we take this expansion and
act on it using a position bra Vector
this inner product becomes a direct
Delta which says that this integral is
zero everywhere except when X Tilda
equals
x so this inner product of the state s
of t and a position igen state X is
another way of expressing the position
wave function s of T and X which gives
the probability amplitudes for each exp
position if we take the Schrodinger
equation and apply a position igen State
bra Vector we see the position wave
function also obeys the shringer
equation I'll say that I am skipping
some steps here for pulling the
hamiltonian operator out in front of the
bra but there's a video by Quantum sense
that explains how to do this and I've
linked it in the
description even if the exact position X
is not known we can still find the
expected value of x by performing a
weighted average over all possible exp
positions weighted by their respective
probabilities this expression can be
Rewritten in several different
ways now I want to stress that the true
schinger equation is about the time
evolution of the abstract State Vector s
of T the position wave function version
of the Schrodinger equation is just one
possible representation of the schinger
equation in the position igen State
basis we could just as easily apply
momentum igen states to the S oft State
and get the momentum wave function
version
instead so the schinger equation is
really about the time evolution of the
state Vector s of
T the key idea behind the shringer
equation is the equivalence of the
hamiltonian operator and the time
derivative operator time
ihar with some rearranging this says the
time derivative operator is equivalent
to the hamiltonian divided by
ihar if you watched video 16 on Lee
algebras you'll know that exponential
ating a derivative operator gives a
translation operator for functions the
proof of this involves the tailor series
and you can pause if you want to go
through
it so if we have a state Vector s of T
and we operate on it with e to the delta
T times the time derivative operator we
shift the state s of T forward in time
by delta T we call this exponential the
time Evolution oper operator and we
denote it by
U now a key property of the time
Evolution operator is that it must be
unitary meaning its Herm Mission
conjugate equals its inverse here's why
at any given time the state s of T
should have a length of one this
indicates the total probability of all
outcomes is
one if we move forward in time by a
duration delta T you using the time
Evolution operator the total probability
over all outcomes must still be
one since the KET State time evolves
with u the corresponding bra state will
time evolve with the hermiss conjugate
UD dagger the only way this
transformation keeps the length of Sai
unchanged is if UD dagger and U cancel
with each other so this means UD dagger
must equal U inverse
so since UD dagger equals U inverse the
time Evolution operator U is a unitary
operator this unitary property
guarantees that probability is conserved
over time this is a core principle in
quantum
mechanics I will say that technically
speaking it's actually the squared
magnitudes of State inner products that
we want to preserve over time and
technically speaking there's another
type of operator called an anti-unitary
operator which also achieves this
however the time Evolution operator U is
unitary so I'm not going to worry about
anti-unitary operators in this
video now we can relate this unitary
property back to Schrodinger's equation
if we look at
generators when a group transformation
can be written as an exponential of a
parameter times an object object G we
call G the Transformations
generator we've seen that the time
derivative operator d by DT is the
generator for time Evolution also called
time
translation however it's a fact from
classical physics that the hamiltonian
which is sort of like energy also
generates time
translations I'm not going to go into
the details here but you can once again
check out quantum sense's video on this
in the description if you want to learn
more Quantum sense has a whole playlist
on the fundamentals of quantum mechanics
that I highly
recommend anyway since dbdt and the
hamiltonian both generate time
translations it's tempting to set them
equal to each other however there are a
couple problems with this first of all I
proved in Video 17 that the generators
of unitary transformations must be
anti-mission meaning they equal the
negative of their Herm Mission conjugate
you can pause here if you want to see
the
proof now we've already declared that
operators that correspond to physical
observables like energy must be Herm
Mission since those give real igen
values so the hamiltonian operator is
Herm Mission not
anti-mission but we can fix this by
including a a factor of the complex I
which picks up an extra negative sign
when you take its Herm Mission
conjugate so I'm going to replace the
operator H with h over I which is an
anti-mission
operator the second problem is that the
units in this equation don't match we
have one over time on one side and
energy on the other side so I'm going to
include a constant H bar with units of
energy time time to make the units work
the result is the essence of the
schinger equation that the time
derivative operator equals the
hamiltonian operator divided IH bar both
of these are generators for the unitary
time Evolution operator so they are
equal this might look more familiar as
Schrodinger's equation if we multiply
both sides by iar and apply it to a
state vector
and so this is what the shringer
equation is all about it says that the
time Evolution generator is anti-h
hermiss and so this generates a unitary
time Evolution operator which guarantees
that total probability is preserved over
time now I mentioned that classical
mechanics tells us energy generates time
translations it's also true that
momentum P generates space translations
in X this means for position wave
functions where the X operator is simply
the X variable the momentum operator
divided by ihar will give us a generator
for space translations which is the
partial derivative of
x it's also true in classical mechanics
that position X generates momentum
translations in P so for momentum wave
functions where the momentum operator is
just the P variable the position
operator divided by IH bar will give us
a generator for momentum translations
which is the partial derivative of
P this procedure of taking classical
variables and replacing them with their
Quantum operators is called canonical
quantization because we're using the
canonical variables X and P from
hamiltonian
mechanics this is the standard procedure
we use to turn a classical Theory into a
Quant quum
Theory now these two quantization
procedures depend on a choice of
position or momentum
basis however there's a more abstract
quantization rule that encompasses both
of them which is declaring that the
position and momentum operators do not
commute and have a commutator of
ihar this quantization rule does not
depend on our choice of basis for States
we'll see this Quant ization procedure
again when we get to Quantum field
Theory now the fact that position and
momentum don't commute means there are
no states that have igen values for both
position and
momentum this means it's impossible to
know both the position and momentum of a
particle at the same time with exact
Precision this is one version of
Heisenberg's uncertainty
principle the last Topic in mechanics
I'll talk about is the Quantum harmonic
oscillator which is a Quantum system for
one particle whose hamiltonian contains
a standard kinetic energy term plus a
quadratic potential energy term similar
to a spring on a mass in classical
physics while the energy levels of this
system have known wave functions the
wave functions are difficult to solve
for there's an easier way to solve for
the energy levels where we take the X
and P operators and use them to Define
two operators a and its Herm Mission
conjugate a dagger this can Loosely be
thought of as changing variables in a 2d
plane from a pair of real numbers X and
Y to a pair of coordinates given by a
complex number Zed and its complex
conjugate these new operators a and a
dagger have a commutator of one or or
the identity
operator this lets us rewrite the
hamiltonian in a much simpler form where
the number operator n hat gives an
integer IG value n for the nth energy IG
State the energies of these igen states
are the IG values of the hamiltonian
operator the ground state at n equal 0
has a nonzero energy of 1 12 H * Omega
and from there each additional energy
level gains H time Omega in
energy the a dagger and a operators are
called raising and lowering operators or
ladder operators because they help us
move between the different energy igen
State
vectors we'll see later that
understanding the quantum harmonic
oscillator is fundamental to
understanding Quantum Fields so keep
this in mind for later
I'll quickly mention that the approach
of evolving the state sigh forward in
time using the time Evolution operator U
is called the schinger
picture we can instead choose to keep
the states constant and evolve
observable operators in time instead
using UD dagger and U this is called the
Heisenberg picture and it has more
obvious parallels with the hamiltonian
formulation of classical mechanics
where Pome brackets are replaced with
commutators so we've gone over the three
areas of physics that come out of
Newtonian physics special relativity
quantum mechanics and classical field
Theory now let's start uniting them
first we'll look at relativistic field
Theory I've already said that the
Maxwell equations from electricity and
magnetism are consistent with special
relativity because the form of the
equations doesn't change under Lorent
Transformations so they are relativistic
field
theories however the field Theory
formulation of Newtonian gravity is not
consistent with special relativity
unlike Maxwell's equations there is only
one plusone equation for gravity and
there are space derivatives but no time
derivatives this equation also changes
form under the Loren
Transformations Newtonian Gra acts
instantaneously everywhere in the
universe unconstrained by the speed of
light and also forces look different
depending on which Lorent boosted frame
you choose due to the effects of length
contraction so it is not a relativistic
field Theory to fix this problem we need
to invent general relativity but we're
not going to worry about that here
instead we're going to take a look at
some of the different types of fields
that can exist which are compatible with
special relativity in particular we'll
look at Klein Gordon fields which are
scaler or spin zero Fields der fields
which are spinner or spin one half
fields and pra fields which are vector
or spin one
Fields if you take the proca field
equation and set the mass to zero you
get the Maxwell fields we know from
electricity and
magnetism we've already seen how
visualizing a field of coupled masses on
Springs gives us the Klein Gordon lran
whose equation of motion is the Klein
Gordon
equation now let's take a quick look at
the Maxwell equations for a vector
field now this version of the Maxwell
equations might look different than the
versions you're used to this capital A
is a four Vector field with four
components and this is called the
electromagnetic four potential it's made
up of one electric potential component
and three magnetic potential
components as I said before we can take
derivatives of potential fields to get
force
fields and this combination of
derivatives of a gives us the Faraday
tensor F which is a 4x4 Matrix that
combines the electric and magnetic
fields into a single object so this
version of the Maxwell equations written
either with a or F is equivalent to this
pair of the more familiar Maxwell
equations but with the source charges
and currents set to
zero recall that we can get the Klein
Gordon equation by starting with the
Klein Gordon Lan density and putting it
through the oiler lrange
equations similarly these Maxwell
equations can also be derived from this
Maxwell lran density if we put it
through the oiler lrange equations
if we want to take Source charges and
currents into account using the four
current J we can use this modified
version of the lran density which gives
Maxwell equations with Source charges
and currents
included now waves in the
electromagnetic field which are light
waves have no Mass so there is no Mass
term in the Maxwell lran
density however we can include a mass
term if we want
and this gives us the pra lonian density
from which we can derive the procha
equation the pra equation describes
massive Vector Fields I'm not sure if
this has any applications in classical
physics but in quantum mechanics this
describes the W and Zed boson Fields
involved with the weak
interaction there is also the dur
equation for modeling a field of spinner
objects and this can be derived DED from
the derler grangian
density again I'm not sure if anything
in real life is modeled by a classical
spinner field but we can still consider
what a classical spinner field would
look like
mathematically in quantum mechanics this
will help us describe the spin 1/2
matter
particles the key idea with these
classical Fields is that we can know the
exact position and momentum of every
part of the field at all times this is
unlike Quantum field Theory where the
uncertainty principle places limits on
what we can know about the field
positions and momenta at the same time
each of these classical Fields has a
Quantum equivalent where the field
variables become Quantum operators and
we'll talk about this
later now let's look at relativistic
quantum
mechanics now the correct way to
generalize quantum mechanics to include
special relativity involves Quantum
Fields but historically speaking
physicists did not understand the need
for Quantum Fields
immediately instead early attempts at
combining quantum mechanics with special
relativity focused on trying to make a
relativistic version of the position
schinger equation we're going to see
that this leads to an inconsistent
Theory but I'm going to go through it
anyway for historical reasons
now I mentioned before that the true
Schrodinger equation gives the time
evolution of an abstract State Vector
however if we apply a position bra
Vector we get the position wave function
version of the Schrodinger equation for
a single
particle this might trick you into
thinking that the position wave function
is a space-time field similar to the
electric field because it depends on
time and space but this is is not
true if we had two particles we would
use a bra State Vector with two particle
positions which would result in a wave
function with two x value inputs one for
each
particle and for three particles this
would involve three x value
inputs so Quantum wave functions do not
live in our standard four-dimensional
space time wave functions live in an
abstract State space that can use any
number of variables required to describe
the state of the
system but again for historical reasons
let's try to generalize the position
schinger equation so that it is
compatible with special
relativity using the standard kinetic
energy and potential energy terms from
classical physics and applying the
quantization rules we see that the
shringer equation for a single particle
has a first derivative in time and a
second derivative in space and the
equation will change form if we use a
Lorent
transformation which means it is not
compatible with special
relativity we can try to fix this by
starting instead with the mass energy
momentum relation from special
relativity and applying quantization
rules to that
instead note that this doesn't contain a
potential energy term so we're ignoring
potential energy here
since energy and momentum are both
squared in the original equation time
and space both end up with second
derivatives in the quantized
equation after quantization each term
has a factor of iar all squared this
allows us to pull out negative H squar
in
front these negative signs inside the
brackets can be ignored since they
Square 2 +
1 this gives us an equation for a wave
function where both time and space have
second
derivatives we can rewrite these
derivatives using Einstein summations
with the menovsky metric Ada we can then
bring the terms to one side and use the
metric to raise one of the indices on a
derivative this actually gives us the
Klein Gordon equation but for the
position wave function of a single
particle this second derivative operator
is sometimes written using a square
symbol called the
dersin and we often choose units where
the speed of light C and H bar are
one the Klein Gordon equation does obey
special relativity and Len's
Transformations this is interesting
because we have now arrived at the Klein
Gordon equation using two different
approaches the first was a 100%
classical field inspired by masses on
Springs where the exact position and
momentum of every part of the field is
known at all
times now we have the Klein Gordon
equation representing the wave function
of a single particle where the wave
function is related to finding the
position of a particle at a specific
time this tells us that the Klein Gordon
equation is not really about quantum
mechanics
specifically instead it's a generic
differential equation for a function
that obeys relativistic physics
however the Klein Gordon equation has
some problems when applied to quantum
mechanics as it can lead to negative
probability densities which doesn't make
any
sense to see why this happens let's
compare the shringer equation and kle
Gordon equation for position wave
functions the Schrodinger equation has a
first order derivative in time and the
Klein Gordon equation has a second order
derivative in time
this means that for the shringer
equation if we specify the wave function
at an initial time T KN this will
completely determine the wave function's
Evolution over
time for the Klein Gordon equation we
need to specify both the wave function
and the wave function's time derivative
at an initial time T knot in order to
determine the wave function's Evolution
over
time this freedom to choose the wave
function's initial derivative
means the wave function has no
probabilistic interpretation as we'll
see
shortly for the Schrodinger equation the
squared magnitude of the wave function
does work as a valid probability density
because it is always non- negative and
it also obeys a continuity equation so
probability is
conserved this means that the total
probability over all space does not
increase or decrease over time time for
the Klein Gordon equation the squared
magnitude of the wave function is non-
negative but it is not
conserved there is a conserved quantity
that we can Define but it can be made to
be negative because we are free to
choose the initial values of both s and
the time derivative of s to give us a
negative number in this
formula so it seems like the Klein
Gordon equation is a failure for
relativistic quantum
mechanics dur tried to fix the failures
of the Klein Gordon equation by finding
an equation with only a first derivative
in time to prevent the probability
density from becoming
negative dur tried to fix this by trying
to find a kind of square root of the
Klein Gordon equation and factoring it
into two parts involving only first
order
derivatives however this was only
possible if the coefficients involved
were 4x4 matrices which are the gamma
matrices without realizing it dur
invented the cl13 SpaceTime Clifford
algebra we saw in previous
videos if we take one of the factors in
this formula and set it to zero we get
the dur
equation since the gamma matrices in
this equation are 4x4 matrices the S
wave function OB object is actually a
four component object called a direct
spinner the four components keep track
of the spin up and spin down States for
both positive and negative energy
solutions for a spin one half
particle the good news with this direct
equation is that there is a resulting
quantity that is non- negative and
conserved over time so it can be
interpreted as a probability density the
direct equation also makes some good
predictions like better predictions for
hydrogen atom energy levels and also
predicting the Magnetic Moment for spin
1/2
particles however the direct equation
still has some
problems the biggest problem is that
there are both positive energy and
negative energy solutions to the dir
equation this means that in theory a
particle at some energy level could drop
down to the next energy level level and
then the next one and on and on forever
releasing an infinite amount of energy
which doesn't make sense dur tried to
fix this problem by proposing that the
negative energy states were all already
occupied by an infinite number of
particles an argument that was later
called the dra C but this argument is
pretty
suspicious so so far in our attempts to
make a relativistic theory of quantum
mechanics our approach was to claim that
the schinger equation was wrong because
it had one time derivative and two space
derivatives and therefore was not
compatible with special relativity we
then searched for a relativistic
equation that would replace the schinger
equation in special relativity but we
kept failing and finding more
problems this is partly because our
approach is fundamentally not correct
remember the core meaning of the
schinger equation is that the time
evolution of states is unitary and so
the total probability is preserved over
time as the state evolves over
time this unitary time Evolution
property is fundamentally true in both
relativistic and non-relativistic
quantum mechanics and so the schinger
equation is true in both relativistic
and non-relativistic quantum mechanics
we should not be trying to get rid of
the schinger equation when trying to
create a relativistic quantum
theory it turns out that if we want to
correctly interpret the dur equation we
need to move to Quantum field Theory
which is where we take classical field
Theory and apply the rules of quantum
mechanics to it so now let's see how we
combine quantum mechanics and field
Theory
together first I want to point out that
in real life experiments
physicists have seen that particles can
be created and
destroyed for example an electron and
its antimatter counterpart the positron
can annihilate with each other and
create a pair of
photons or in beta Decay a neutron is
converted into a proton and this creates
an electron and anti-neutrino in the
process so in order to be able to
explain these phenomena we need to be
able to allow for Quantum states to
transition between different particle
types or even different numbers of
particles we're going to have to leave
behind the idea of a wave function for a
single particle evolving over time
because this does not allow changes in
particle type or particle
number instead we're going to take some
inspiration from the quantum harmonic
oscillator and its raising and lowering
operators we're going to imagine in a
whole field of quantum oscillators each
with their own ladder
operators and when we excite one of
these oscillators that is the same thing
as creating a particle at that location
in the field so we're going to start
viewing particles as excitations in a
field of quantum oscillators which is
also called a Quantum
field each particle type will have its
own Quantum
field a key change we need to make is to
start interpreting our Quantum State s
of t as representing the state of an
entire Quantum field instead of just the
state of a single
particle with a field we can create and
Destroy as many particles as we like
because particles are interpreted to be
excitations in the
field to see how Quantum Fields work
let's go back to classical fields in In
classical physics we made a classical
field by joining two classical
oscillators together and then joining
together more and more oscillators until
we got an entire classical field of
oscillators to get a quantum field we do
something similar we start by joining
two Quantum oscillators together and
then join together more and more until
we get an entire field of quantum
oscillators which we call a Quantum
field let's start with a pair of quantum
harmonic oscillators labeled one and two
each oscillator has its own Quantum
State sigh along with its own operators
for position momentum and raising and
lowering energy
states when combining systems together
in quantum mechanics we use the tensor
product so the state of the combined
oscillator system lives in the tensor
product space of the two original
systems State
spaces so we could for example label
coupled oscillator States using two
position labels which would be the
tensor product of two position igen
states for the individual
oscillators this represents a state
where the positions of the two
oscillators are exactly known but the
momenta for the two oscillators is
completely unknown
we can similarly Define a state where
both momenta are exactly known but the
positions are completely
unknown we can Define two position
operators X1 hat and X2 hat which act on
the combined position IG State and
return the oscillator positions as IG
values to be technically correct X1 hat
is actually a position operator tensored
with an identity
operator when this acts on the combined
position igen State the position
operator acts on the first oscillator
State and the identity operator acts on
the second oscillator
State the position operator Returns the
position IG value and the identity
operator leaves the state
unchanged the overall returned igen
value is the position of the first
oscillator we have a similar tensor
product definition for for the second
position operator as well as the two
momentum
operators we can similarly Define
raising and lowering operators which
raise and lower the energy states on
each individual
oscillator now a key idea here is that
we can know the positions of both
oscillators exactly at the same time
mathematically speaking this means the
commutator of the X1 and X2 position
operators is zero we can verify this by
writing the position operators
explicitly using tensor products and use
the tensor product rule of applying left
elements to left elements and applying
right elements to right
elements we see the terms cancel and so
the commutator is zero this means that
there are states that have simultaneous
igen values for both the X1 and X2
operators similarly we can know both
moment
of both oscillators at the same time so
the two momentum operators
commute it's also possible to know one
oscillator's position exactly and know
the other oscillator's momentum exactly
so operators from different oscillators
always
commute it's only the position and
momentum from the same oscillator which
cannot be known together at the same
time so these commutators are non
zero the same is true for the
commutators of ladder
operators we can summarize these
commutator relations using the chroniker
Delta where the I and J indices indicate
the one and two labels for the
oscillators now the hamiltonian for our
oscillator system is the same one we saw
in classical physics with kinetic energy
terms spring potential energy en terms
and a coupling potential energy term for
the rubber band connecting the
masses the only difference is that the X
and P variables are quantized and are
now non-commuting Quantum
operators now in classical physics we
saw this system was difficult to solve
until we found the normal modes which
were two completely independent
Solutions we could add together in
different amounts to get more
complicated Solutions
the first normal mode had the masses
oscillating together and the second
normal mode had the masses oscillating
in opposite
directions we can also use these normal
modes in quantum mechanics we'll Define
the first mode big X1 as X1 + X2 the
masses moving together and the second
mode big X2 will be X1 - X2 the masses
moving in opposite
directions we can have similar
definitions for the momenta of the
normal modes big P1 and big
P2 I'm also going to scale these
formulas by 1 over the < TK of two for
normalization
purposes if we rewrite the hamiltonian
using these big variables the coupling
term disappears showing that the two
normal modes are indeed independent from
each
other also note that the rubber band
constant Kappa has now been absorbed
absorbed into the spring constant term
so we now have new spring constants big
K1 and big
K2 so the small x's and small PS are
used for measuring the positions and
momenta of the individual oscillators
one and two but the big x's and big PS
are used for measuring the positions and
momenta of the two normal
modes interestingly you can check that
the big x's and big PS obey the same
same commutation relations as the small
x's and small
PS so it's possible to measure the exact
positions of both normal modes at the
same time or measure the momenta of both
normal modes at the same time but we
can't know the exact position and exact
momentum of the same normal mode at the
same time which is why this commutator
is
nonzero also just as we can Define the
small a ladder operators for the energy
levels of individual ual masses we can
also Define the big a ladder operators
for the energy levels of individual
normal
modes these allow us to raise and lower
the energy states for the normal modes
they also obey the same commutation
relations as the small
A's and the hamiltonian written with the
big a operators looks like this where
these number operators count the energy
levels of each normal mode and the
normal mode each have their own
frequencies big Omega 1 and big Omega 2
which Define the quantized steps between
their energy
levels so we have the original small x's
and PS for measuring position and
momenta of individual masses we can use
these to define the small a ladder
operators for changing energy levels of
individual masses we can also Define the
big x's and big PS which measure the
positions and momenta of the normal
modes of the system this causes the
terms in the hamiltonian to decouple
making it
simpler and we can Define the big a
ladder operators for changing energy
levels of individual normal
modes the conversion equations between
all these operators are given
here now we can add more and more
Quantum oscillators so that we have an
infinite collection of oscillators each
with their own X variable denoted by a
subscript label
I we usually turn this diagram on its
side so that the oscillators move in the
FI Direction and are labeled with a
continuous variable X so f of x will
measure the extension of the oscillator
at location X this is what we call a
Quantum
field just like before each oscillator
has its own Quantum state that lives in
its own Hilbert space the quantum state
of the entire field lives in a space
which is the tensor product of all these
individual Hilbert
spaces so the coupled Quantum oscillator
had two position operators X1 hat and X2
hat our Quantum field with its infinite
oscillators will have an infinite number
of position operators Fiat of X for all
the various X locations along the
continuous x
axis for the coupl oscillators exact
position I states were labeled with a
pair of position X values and the xat
position operators would act on this IG
state to return the position IG value
associated with one particular
oscillator for the quantum field exact
position igen states are labeled with an
infinite number of five values basically
an entire function of known five
values the five hat position operators
would act on this igen state to return
the IG value associated with one
particular
oscillator so with the coupled
oscillators the X's are the dynamical
variables we measure and the oscillators
are labeled by a subscript number but
for Quantum Fields the fi's are the
dynamical variables that we measure and
the oscillators are labeled by a
continuous X
parameter so in Quantum fields X is no
longer a dynamical variable we measure X
is just a label for identifying a
position in a
field also just as the coupled
oscillators had two momentum operators
P1 hat and P2 hat our Quantum field has
an infinite number of momentum operators
Pi hat of X for all the various X
locations along the continuous
xais in the coupled oscillators exact
momentum IG states were labeled with a
pair of momentum P values and the P hat
momentum operators would act on these IG
states to return the momentum IG values
associated with one particular
oscillator for the quantum field the
exact momentum IG states are labeled
with an infinite number of pi values the
pi hat momentum operators would then act
on this IG state to return the momentum
IG value associated with one particular
oscillator
for the coupled oscillators I mentioned
that the operators are technically
tensor products with an identity
operator and this allows them to pick
out the specific state in the tensor
product to act
on this is also true with Quantum field
operators but there are an infinite
number of identity operators in the
tensor product since there are an
infinite number of oscillator states in
the tensor
product for the coupled oscillators I
said it was always possible to know the
exact positions and exact momenta of
different oscillators at the same time
but it's forbidden to know the exact
position and exact momentum of the same
oscillator at the same time so it's only
X and P for the same oscillator that
have a nonzero commutator indicated by
this chroner Delta when I and J are
equal it's the same with Quantum fields
we can know exact positions and exct
momenta of different oscillators at the
same time but it's forbidden to know the
exact position and exact momentum of the
same oscillator at the same time so it's
only fi and Pi for the same oscillator
that have a nonzero
commutator indicated by this direct
Delta when X1 and X2 are
equal and just as we can make ladder
operators for the coupled oscillators
using linear combinations of X and P
we can make ladder operators for the
field oscillators using linear
combinations of fi and pi and they obey
the expected commutation
relations now the Klein Gordon field has
this hamiltonian density with kinetic
energy density added to the potential
energy
density in Quantum field Theory all
these F get promoted to Quantum
operators this is called called field
quantization it is sometimes called
second quantization but that's a bad
name that comes from a historical
misunderstanding physicists used to
think that they had to quantize the
energy momentum relation to get the
Klein Gordon equation and then quantize
it again to get the quantized Klein
Gordon field but really we're just
taking the classical Klein Gordon field
and quantizing it
once if you recall we can Define
conjugate momentum density Pi for a
field using a derivative of the lonian
density and for the Klein Gordon field
this field momentum density is just the
time derivative of the field
amplitude so we can replace the time
derivative of fi hat with pi hat this
makes the hamiltonian density look more
like our coupled oscillator
hamiltonian recall that it's easier to
understand the hamiltonian if we rewrite
it using normal modes for Klein Gordon
Fields the normal modes are sinusoidal
traveling waves and remember the angular
frequency Omega and the angular wave
number K obey this Mass
relation for convenience we can rewrite
this cosine as a complex exponential
this lets us split up the factors for
time space and phase the phase Factor
can be absorbed into the overall
amplitude making the amplitude a complex
number if we want to get the original
real field back we can just take the
real part of this complex
field also while the field technically
depends on both time and space for the
remainder of this video we're going to
take the special case where all the
operators act at the same constant time
so we're going to be ignoring the time
parameter of the
field now with the coupled Quantum
oscillators we combined the two
oscillator position operators in linear
combination using the normal mode
coefficients to get the big X position
operators for normal modes we can do
something similar for oscillators in the
Klein Gordon field we can combine the
various fi position operators together
using normal mode coefficients given by
these complex
exponentials since X is a continuous
variable the linear combination over X
is done using an integral over X the
result is the operator big fi which
measures the position of a specific
normal mode with wave number K which is
related to the mod's momentum P using
H this transformation between operators
for individual oscillators and operators
for entire normal modes is the forier
transform the transformation between
small X and big X in and the coupled
oscillators was also a 4A transform but
this is less obvious since there were
only two terms in the sum which gives
coefficients of + one and
minus1 we can use a similar fora
transform formula for the pi momentum
operators to get the big Pi operator
which is the field momentum operator for
the normal mode with wave number
K we can also get the inverse formulas
that change from Big F and big Pi back
to fi and Pi these inverse
Transformations have opposite signs on
the
exponentials also in the convention I'm
using both of these 4A formulas have a
factor of 1 over the < TK of 2 pi in
front some other sources will use a
convention where both of these factors
are on the inverse formula
only it's also worth noting that if we
take the inverse fora transform formula
and then sub in the 4A transform formula
for big fi we should get the original
small fi result back again we can prove
this is true by grouping these
exponentials together and then using the
property that this integral over an
exponential of K is a definition of the
direct Delta this allows us to remove
one of the integrals and replace X Tilda
with X showing that we do indeed end up
with the original f hat
operator this definition of the direct
Delta works because if the X and X Tilda
values here are different the complex
exponential becomes a sinusoid and this
integrates to zero if we integrate from
negative to positive
Infinity but for xal X Tilda the
exponential in the integral becomes one
and we end up with an infinite Spike
just like a direct
Delta now now since we're using complex
numbers in this Fier transform I do have
a few notes to add first the big fi and
big Pi operators are no longer Herm
Mission operators because of the use of
complex numbers so their igen values are
now complex
numbers this is because the amplitudes
in front of complex waves contain both
magnitude information and phase
information because of these complex
numbers when writing the hamiltonian
density instead of writing the squares
of operators we're going to write the
squared magnitude of operators which is
equal to the dagger of the operator
times the operator
itself now our fi and Pi operators still
represent real Fields with real
observable igen values so they are still
Herm Mission
operators as a result it can be shown
that their Fier transforms bigf and big
Pi have a special property where their
Herm Mission conjugate equals the same
operator but with the negative wave
number this is a property that will come
up
later also you can pause on this slide
to see the proof of how to get the
commutator of big fi and big Pi note
that the direct Delta here has a plus
sign between the
K's so with the coupled oscillators we
liked the normal mode oper ators because
they gave a simplified hamiltonian and
got rid of the coupling
term the same is true for the Klein
Gordon hamiltonian density so what we'd
like to do is take small fi and Pi which
are functions of position X and replace
them with big fi and Pi which are
functions of normal mode wave number K
to do this I'm going to go through a few
properties
quickly first is paral theorem which
says that the integral over the squared
magnitude of a function is equal to the
integral over the squared magnitude of
its forier
transform this applies to both fi and
Pi this is true because the forier
transform is a unitary transform which
means it's kind of like a rotation that
doesn't change the norm of
functions you can pause here to view the
proof of pars of all's theorem if you
want
paral theorem will help us transform the
first two terms in the hamiltonian
density but we also need to transform
the coupling term with the X derivative
of
fi if we take this derivative and
replace fi with the inverse fora
transform the X derivative only touches
this complex exponential which brings
out a factor of i k in front if we take
the squared magnitude of this we end up
with the squared magnitude of K in the
integral which is really just k^ s since
K is a real number indicating the wave
number now let's take our hamiltonian
density and integrate it over X using
parel's theorem we know we can change
the first two terms into integrals over
K of the Fier transformed
functions and we get a similar result
with the X derivative term but we can
replace the derivatives with factors of
K and front like we saw
before if we look at all the terms in
this integral over K this gives us a new
hamiltonian density operator which I'm
calling H Tilda hat although I will
often leave out the Tilda later in this
video this measures energy density for
the normal mode with wave number
K also using this Mass relation we can
rewrite m^2 + k^2 with the angular
frequency Omega s which is a function of
K as promised we can indeed see that the
hamiltonian when written with the normal
modes is simpler because the coupling
term has
disappeared and again with the coupled
Quantum oscillators there was one last
change of basis to the Big A's which
gave us the big a ladder operators for
specific normal modes with specific
frequencies we can Define similar big a
operators for our Klein Gordon field and
these let us create or destroy normal
modes with wave number K in our
field notice that these formulas involve
negative K as an argument here this is
related to the fact that the big fi and
big Pi operators are non Herm
Mission you can pause the video here if
you want to see how to rewrite the
hamiltonian density using big a
operators it can also be shown that the
big a operators obey these commutation
relations so when people talk about
General Solutions of the Klein Gordon
field you'll often see F ofx expressed
using an integral over all possible
normal modes and then big fi is usually
Rewritten as a linear combination of the
big a ladder
operators after splitting the integral
into two and flipping some of the signs
for K we get this Final Solution here
for 5x expanded out in terms of normal
mode ladder
operators there's also a similar General
solution for pi of X written like
this for coupled oscillators we also
defined the number operator n for
counting the energy levels of a specific
normal mode I for Quantum fields we can
define a similar number operator for
counting the energy level of the normal
mode with wave number K the pH physical
interpretation of this is that n hat
counts the number of particles with wave
number K if we include a factor of H bar
this lets us count the number of
particles with momentum p in the
field now there is a well-known problem
with writing the Klein Gordon
hamiltonian density in terms of number
operators we get this term involving a
direct Delta of zero which gives
Infinity this seems to be implying that
the Klein Gordon field has an infinite
energy density even when there are no
particles present for practical
calculations we ignore this term since
we only care about energy differences
and since this infinite term appears in
both the initial and final States it
will cancel out on both sides there's a
lot more you could say about this term
but I'm not going to bother talking
about it in this
video so to sum up we have position and
momentum operators for each oscillator
fi and Pi we have the small a ladder
operators for changing individual
oscillator energy levels we also have
big fi and big Pi operators for the
normal mode positions and
momenta and we also have the big a
ladder operators for changing energy
levels of the normal
modes and these are the equations that
relate
them most Quantum field Theory text
books tend to focus only on the original
operators and the normal mode ladder
operators since these are the operators
most useful for
calculations but personally I find it
confusing when the other operator types
are not included in the
explanation now remember in Quantum
field Theory we interpret particles as
excitations in a field the small a
ladder operators allow us to create and
Destroy particles at a specific position
and the big a ladder operators allow us
to create and Destroy particles with a
specific
momentum so we can apply these small a
creation operators to the vacuum state
to create particles at specific
positions since creation operators at
different locations commute the order of
creation doesn't matter applying the
creation operator at the same position
twice will create create two particles
at that
position the same is true for the
equivalent big a momentum operators and
their
states normally we would have to write
position or momentum igen States using
an infinite number of labels specifying
how many particles are in each possible
position or momentum state but we
usually leave out the states with zero
particles and only write the labels for
states with a nonzero number of
particles
just like in ordinary quantum mechanics
we can evolve these Quantum States
forward in time using the time Evolution
operator given by exponentiating the
hamiltonian operator for the field but
this process ends up being a lot more
complicated for Fields since the
hamiltonian of a field is the integral
of The Field's hamiltonian density I
won't be discussing how to calculate
this in this video
now if you'll recall in single particle
quantum mechanics each possible position
igen State X of a particle had a
probability amplitude associated with it
which was the value of the wave function
s of T and X for that
position we got this probability
amplitude by projecting the bra position
State X onto the quantum State s of T
and the wave function s of T and X obeys
the schinger
equation the same is true for Quantum
Fields a field igen State f is a state
where the exact field value of every
oscillator in the field is exactly
known each possible field Ian State fi
of a field has a probability associated
with it which is the value of the
quantum wave functional s of T and fi
for a given field state
Fi we're saying SII is a functional
because it takes a function fi as input
and returns a complex
number we get this probability amplitude
by projecting the bra field State fi
onto the quantum State s of T and the
wave functional s of T and fi obeys the
shringer
equation so it's important to know the
Schrodinger equation still applies in
Quantum field Theory but the wave
function does not live in position space
it lives in the space of all possible
fields and the shringer equation makes
sure the time evolution is unitary so
that probabilities are preserved over
time now this wave functional is usually
too complicated to deal with directly
and we usually have to work with normal
mode field Solutions instead to simplify
things but conceptually the wave
functional for the quantum field does
exist and it does obey Schrodinger's
equation and evolves according to
unitary time
Evolution also just as we can write the
momentum operator P hat using an X
derivative in position space we can also
write the field momentum density
operator Pi hat using something called a
functional derivative of the field fi
but I'm not going to discuss that
here so the key takeaway I want you to
get from this video is that quantum
mechanics and Quantum field Theory are
not two totally different theories both
involve a Quantum State s of T that
evolves according to Schrodinger's
equation and obeys unitary time
Evolution it's just that the states for
quantum mechanics involve individual
positions or momenta for individual
particles whereas States in Quantum
field Theory correspond to possible
field configurations or field momentum
configurations for an entire field of
quantum
oscillators the inner product of these
IG states with the state s of T gives
the probability amplitude of the state s
of T collapsing onto that igen
state so hopefully that gives you an
idea for what a Quant Quantum field
is now let's bring all of this together
into relativistic Quantum field Theory
which most people just call Quantum
field
Theory we've already learned about
several relativistic classical field
equations the Klein Gordon equation for
scalar Fields the dur equation for
spinner fields and the procha equation
for Vector fields we can also calculate
the field momentum density for each of
these fields Fields using the usual
formula now if we want to quantize these
fields we can take the field and field
momentum variables and impose the
quantization condition which forces the
fields and field momenta to obey
commutation relations or
anti-commutation relations in the case
of the direct
equation after quantization the lunian
and hamiltonian densities are now
operators Written In terms of the field
operators we can also change the
operator basis to the creation and
Annihilation operators which let us
create and Destroy particles in the
field although I should mention that
creating spinner and Vector particles is
a bit more complicated because these are
multicomponent
objects also note that I'm dealing with
the full three dimensions of space in
these formulas and so the formulas on
this slide use the three thre
dimensional version of the direct Delta
function and the 48 transform formulas
use a factor of 1 over the < TK of 2 pi
taken to the third
power it's also possible to make
different fields interact with each
other by introducing additional terms in
the field lonian or hamiltonian
densities for example this term couples
together the photon field a and the
electron field SII in quantum
ramics allowing photons to interact with
electrons through the electromagnetic
force these interaction terms can make
the field equations of motion
nonlinear meaning the sum of two
solutions is no longer a valid
solution however the shringer equation
for the time evolution of the quantum
state is still
linear now these are all examples of
relativistic quantum fields but what
about non-relativistic Quantum
Fields the difference between
relativistic and non-relativistic
Quantum Fields basically comes down to a
speed limit regarding how quickly one
part of the field can talk to another
part of the field if there is no speed
limit for how fast field disturbances
propagate then we are working with a
non-relativistic Quantum field Theory
and the form of the fields lonian
density will remain the same under
Galilean
Transformations however if the field
disturbances are limited by the speed of
light C we are working with a
relativistic Quantum field Theory and
the form of the fields lran density will
remain the same under Loren
Transformations we've seen several
examples of relativistic quantum fields
which are used in particle physics where
particles are often traveling close to
the speed of light however certain
certain condensed matter systems can be
described with non-relativistic Quantum
fields for example the non-relativistic
shringer field can be used to describe
Bose Einstein condensates or super
fluids I want to be clear that this
might look like the shringer equation
but Sai is not a wave function it's
actually a field operator that
represents coupled oscillators in a
Quantum field and it obeys commutation
Rel
ations here the physical phenomena tend
to travel much slower than the speed of
light so relativistic effects can be
ignored and a non-relativistic field is
sufficient for modeling the physics
properly now everything I've talked
about in this video approaches Quantum
field Theory using the formulation
called second
quantization also called field
quantization or canonical
quantization there's an alternative
formulation of qft called The Path
integral formulation which is based on
the principle of least action but I'm
not going to talk about that
here one very last thing I want to
discuss is the spin statistics theorem
the spin statistics theorem states that
integer spin particles like spin zero
scalers and spin one vectors are always
bons bons have the property that
identical partic
can occupy the same state boson creation
and Annihilation operators obey
commutation relations and bosonic wave
functions are symmetric under the
exchange of two identical particles so
swapping the particles results in the
same wave function value the properties
of super fluidity and super conductivity
are explained by this property of bons
that allows identical particles to exist
in the same
State the theorem also states that all
half integer spin particles like spin
one half Spinners are always
ferons fermion are particles that obey
Po's Exclusion Principle where identical
particles cannot occupy the same state
this is why no two electrons with the
same spin can occupy the same atomic
orbital firon creation and Annihilation
operators OB obey anti-commutation
relations these anti-commutation
relations say that applying a creation
operator for the same state twice gives
zero so it's impossible for two
identical firmon particles to occupy the
same state fironic wave functions are
also
anti-symmetric meaning exchanging two
identical particles results in an extra
negative sign this means that two
identical partic being in the same state
will result in a wave function value of
zero which again means that two
identical firmance being in the same
state is impossible and has probability
zero while the spin statistics theorem
is easy to State it's pretty difficult
to prove and I honestly don't understand
the proofs yet so I won't be proving
them
here now it can take several weeks or
even months to learn the the behind
Quantum fields in a classroom but
learning to solve Quantum field
equations can take additional weeks and
months for example to solve Quantum
electrodynamics problems that involve
electrons positons and photons all
interacting with each other you need to
learn the method of Fineman
diagrams these are often first presented
as cute pictures but each of these
pictures represents a complicated
integral that must be calculated in
order to compute the final result the
technique of
renormalization must also be used for
dealing with diagrams that have
loops these Fineman diagrams come from
using the time Evolution operator on a
Quantum State we can write the time
Evolution operator as the exponential of
the hamiltonian operator and the
hamiltonian operator can be written as
the integral over the hamiltonian
density operator for a given Quantum
field
Theory when this exponential is expanded
as a tailor series we call it a Dyson
series and the various integrals in this
series correspond to Fineman
diagrams the exponent On Any Given term
indicates the number of vertices in the
Fineman diagrams for that
term for predicting Quark interactions
in Quantum chromodynamics it's common to
model space as a lattice and run
computer simulations to see how the
system will evolve over
time Quantum field theory is a bit of a
strange subject because it's possible to
know a lot about the theory and
symmetries of quantum Fields but have no
idea how to solve them whereas it's
possible to know how to solve Quantum
field systems while not knowing a large
portion of the theory in this video
series I will not be teaching any of
these methods for how to solve Quantum
field equations instead I'm just going
to focus on the simpler cases involving
a classical direct field of spinners
where no quantum mechanics is involved
and also seeing how these same solutions
to the direct equation can be
interpreted in relativistic quantum
mechanics and how direct Spinners keep
track of both matter and antimatter for
spin one half
particles I will not be looking at the
direct equation where the quantization
procedure has been applied making it a
true Quantum
field I'll start going through more
careful derivations Solutions and
interpretations of the direct equation
in the next few videos